So, I had been a photographer
عملتُ كمصّورٍ
for 18 years
لمدّة ثمانيةَ عشرَ عاماً
before I began the Microsculpture Project.
قبلَ أنْ أُنشِئَ مشروعي (مايكروسكالبتشر).
And in that time, I had shot global ad campaigns,
وخلالَ تلكَ الفترةِ أُتيحَ لي أنْ أصوّرَ حملاتٍ دعائيّةً عالميّةً
I had the opportunity to photograph some of my generation's icons,
وحظيتُ بفرصةِ التقاطِ صورٍ لمشاهيرَ يعتبرونَ رموزاً
and I was traveling the world.
وقدْ كنتُ أجوبُ العالم.
I got to a point in my career that I dreamed of getting to,
مررتُ في بدايةِ مسيرتي بأوقاتٍ كانَ فيها البدءُ بالعملِ كلَّ ما تمنيته
and yet, for some reason, I still felt a little bit unfulfilled.
لكنّني وبعدَ كلِّ هذا النجاح لم أكنْ أشعرُ بأنّني راضٍ بعد.
Despite the extraordinary things I was shooting and experiencing,
ورغمَ أنَّ الصّورَ التي كنتُ ألتقطها كانتْ فريدةً من نوعها
they'd started to feel a little bit ordinary to me.
لكنّها بدأتْ تبدو عاديّةً بالنسبة لي.
I was also getting concerned
أضِف لذلكَ أنّني كنتُ قلقاً
about how disposable photography had started to feel in the digital world,
مِنْ أنَّ الصورَ الفوتوغرافيّةَ ربّما فقدت قيمتها في ظلِّ التطوّر الرقميّ
and I really wanted to produce images that had a sense of worth again.
وأردتُ بشدّةٍ أنْ أقومَ بشيءٍ يعيدُ لمهنة التصويرِ قيمتها.
And I needed a subject that felt extraordinary.
لكنّني احتجتُ لفكرةٍ مبدعةٍ للقيامِ بهذا
Sometimes I wish I had the eyes of a child.
وتمنّيتُ في بعض الأوقاتِ أنْ أعودُ طفلاً.
And by that I mean, I wish I could look at the world
أعني بأنّني تمنيتُ لو أستطيعُ أنْ أرى العالمَ مجدّداً
in the same as I did when I was a small boy.
بالطريقةِ التي كنتُ أراهُ بها حينما كنتُ طفلاً.
I think there is a danger, as we get older,
من السيّء بأنّه حينما نكبرُ
that our curiosity becomes slightly muted or dulled by familiarity.
لنْ نمتلكَ الفضولَ الذي امتلكناهُ في صغرنا.
And as a visual creator, one of the challenges for me
وأحدُ التحدياتِ التي واجهتني في مهنتي
is to present the familiar in a new and engaging way.
هيَ محاولةُ تقديمِ شيءٍ مألوفٍ بطريقةٍ جديدةٍ مثيرةٍ للاهتمام.
Fortunately for me, though, I've got two great kids
لِحسنِ حظّي حقيقةً لديّ طفلانِ مدهشانِ
who are still curious about the world.
لا يزالانِ يمتلكانِ ذلك الفضول.
Sebastian -- he's still curious about the world, and in 2014, in spring,
في ربيعِ عامِ 2014، جاءَ (سيباستيان) إليَّ بفضولهِ
he brought in a ground beetle from the garden.
وقد أحضرَ خِنفسةً من الحديقة.
There was nothing particularly special about this insect --
لم يكن هناك شيءٌ مميّزٌ في حشرةٍ كهذه
you know, it was a common species.
كانت مجرّدَ مخلوقٍ نألفهُ جميعاً.
But he was still curious,
لكنَّ فُضولهُ تجاه الأشياءِ
and he brought it up to my office,
دفعهُ لإحضارها إليّ
and we decided to look at it under his microscope.
لكيّ نتفحّصها باستخدام مجهرهِ الضوئيّ
He had a little science kit for Christmas.
الذي حصلَ عليه كهديّةٍ في الكريسماس.
And this is what we saw.
وكانَ هذا مارأيناه.
Now, when I first saw this, it blew me away.
عندَ رؤيةَ هذا لأوّلِ مرّة دُهِشتُ جدّاً صراحةً
Up here -- this is the back of the ground beetle.
ما ترونهُ هنا هو صورةُ لظهرِ تلكَ الخنفسة.
When I first saw it, it reminded me of a galaxy.
لكنَّ المشهدَ ذكّرني بصورِ المجرّاتِ في الفضاء.
And all the time, this had just been outside our window.
وقد كانَ كلُّ هذا في حديقةِ منزلي طوالَ الوقت.
You know, I was looking for this extraordinary subject,
كُنتُ أبحثُ كما أخبرتكم عن شيءٍ خارجٍ عن المألوف
and it took Seb's eyes and curiosity to bring it in to me.
وقد تطلّب الأمرُ عينيّ سيباستيان لأجدَ ماكنتُ أبحثُ عنه.
So I decided to photograph it for him, and this is what I produced.
قرّرتُ إذاً أنْ أصوّرَ الخنفسة لهُ وهذهِ هيَ الصّورةُ التي التقطتها.
I basically asked myself two simple questions.
خطرَ لي حينها سؤالانِ في نفسي.
The first one:
السّؤال الأوّل هوَ:
Could I take all my knowledge and skill of photographic lighting
ما الذي سيحصلُ إنْ وضعتُ كاملَ خبرتي في مجالِ التصوير
and take that onto a subject that's five millimeters long?
لأقومَ بإنتاجِ صورٍ لأشياءَ لا يتجاوزُ طولها خمسةَ ميليمترات؟
But also: Could I keep creative control over that lighting
لكنَّ السؤالَ الأهم: هلْ سأتمكّن من إظهارِ لمحةٍ إبداعيّة
on a subject that size?
عندَ تصويرِ شيءٍ بهذا الحجم؟
So I practiced on some other found specimens,
بدأتُ بتصويرِ عيّناتٍ لمخلوقاتٍ أخرى مشابهة
and I approached the Oxford University Museum of Natural History
ثمَّ كلّمتُ إدارةَ متحفِ أوكسفورد المتخصّصِ في تاريخِ العلومِ الطبيعيّة
to see if I could have access to their collection,
لأرى إنْ كانَ بإمكانهم السّماحُ لي بالعملِ على معروضاتهم
to progress the project.
لأتمكّنَ مِن إنجاحِ مشروعي.
And I went up there for a meeting,
وهكذا ذهبتُ إلى اجتماعٍ معهم
and I showed them some of the images that I'd been shooting,
وعرضتُ عليهمُ الصورَ التي التقطتها
and they could see the kind of detail I was able to get.
وباتَ بإمكانهم رؤية نوعيّةِ الصورِ التي بإمكاني التقاطها.
I don't think they'd ever really seen anything quite like it before,
لاأظنُّ بأنّهم كانوا قدْ رأَوْا شيئاً كهذا في السّابق
and from that point forward, they gave me open access
وحصلتُ منذُ تلكَ اللحظةِ على موافقتهم للعملِ على
to their entire collection
أيِّ عيّنةٍ لديهم
and the assistance of Dr. James Hogan, their entomologist.
وعلى خدماتِ عالمِ الحشراتِ (جيمس هوغان) ليساعدني بخبرته.
Now, over the next two-and-a-half years,
وهكذا، خلالَ العامينِ والنّصفِ التاليين
I shot 37 insects from their collection.
صوّرتُ 37 عيّنةً من حشراتهم.
And the way I work
الطريقةُ التي كنتُ أعملُ بها
is that I essentially split the insect up into multiple sections,
هيَ أنْ أقومَ بتجزئةِ جسدِ الحشرةِ إلى عدّةِ أجزاءَ
and I treat each one of those sections like a small still life.
ثمَّ أُعامِلَ كلَّ جزءٍ كما لو كانَ مخلوقاً مستقلّاً بحدّ ذاته.
So for example, if I was photographing the eye of the insect,
لو كنتُ أعملُ مثلاً على تصويرِ عينِ الحشرةِ
which is normally quite smooth and dome-shaped,
وهيَ جُزءٌ لهُ شكلٌ أملسٌ يشبهُ القبّة
then I'd use a light source that is large and soft and diffuse,
سأقومُ حينها باستعمالِ إضاءةٍ لطيفةٍ منتشرةٍ في اتجاهاتٍ عديدة
so I don't get any harsh hot spots on that surface.
لكي تظهرَ التفاصيلُ دونَ نقاطٍ مضاءةٍ أكثرَ من اللازم.
But once my attention turns over to a hairy leg,
أمّا حينما أعملُ مثلاً على تصويرِ قدمٍ مُشعِرةٍ لحشرةٍ
that lighting setup will change completely.
سأقومُ حينها بتعديلِ الإضاءةِ كلّياً.
And so I make that one tiny section look as beautiful as I possibly can,
وهكذا سأجعلُ كلِّ جزءٍ يبدو بأجملِ شكلٍ ممكن
and I work my way across the insect
وسأكرّرُ هذا على كلِّ أجزاءِ الجسد
until I have about 20 or 25 different sections.
إلى أنْ أحصلَ على حواليّ 20 أو 25 جزءٍ مختلف.
The issue with photography at high magnification
المشكلةُ في التقاطِ الصّورِ لأشياءَ صغيرةِ الحجم
is that there is inherently a very shallow depth of field.
هيَ أنَّ التفاصيلَ بكاملها ستكونُ محتواةً في مسافةٍ صغيرةٍ للغاية.
So to get around that, what I do is,
وما أقوم به للتخلّصِ من هذه المشكلة
I put my camera on a rail
هو أن أضعَ الكاميرا على سكّةٍ
that I can automate to move 10 microns in between each shot.
لأتركَ أوتوماتيكيّاً مسافةَ 10 مايكروناتٍ بينَ اللقطةِ والأخرى.
That's about one-seventh the width of a human hair.
وهذا بطولِ سُبعٍ من شعرةِ إنسان.
And then that provides me with a deep stack of images.
وهذا مايمنحني كميّةً هائلةً منَ الصور.
Each has a tiny sliver of focus all the way through.
كلُّ جزءٍ منها مضاءٌ بما يكفي لإظهار تفاصيله.
And I can squash that down
ثمَّ أقومُ بتجميعِ الأجزاءِ وضغطهم سويّةً
to produce one image that is fully focused from front to back.
لأحصُلَ على صورةٍ واحدةٍ مضاءةٍ بكامل تفاصيلها.
So essentially, that gives me 25 sections that are fully focused
وفي النهايةِ يكونُ لديّ 25 جزءاً
and beautifully lit.
مضاؤونَ بأجملِ ما يمكن.
Now, each one of my images
وكلُّ جزءٍ من هذه الأجزاءِ
is made up of anywhere between 8- and 10,000 separate shots.
مكوّنٌ من مابينَ 8 إلى 10 آلافِ لقطةٍ منفصلة.
They take about three-and-a-half weeks to create,
نحتاجُ عادةً حوالَيْ ثلاثةَ أسابيعَ لدمجِ هذهِ الصّور
and the file sizes on average are about four gigabytes.
ويكونُ حجمُ ملفِّ التخزينِ النهائيّ حوالي 4 غيغا بايت.
So I've got plenty of information to play with when I'm printing.
وهكذا يكونُ لديَّ الخيارُ لإظهارِ أيِّ تفصيلٍ أو حذفه من الصورة.
And the prints at the exhibition are around the three-meter mark.
تكونُ الصورُ عادةً بطولِ ثلاثةِ أمتارٍ عند وضعها في المعارض.
In fact, I had a show in Milan two weeks ago,
حقيقةً، كانَ لدينا صورٌ بطولِ تسعةِ أمتارَ
and we had some prints there that were nine meters long.
في معرضٍ أقمناه في (ميلان) الأسبوعَ الماضي.
But, you know, I realize
أعلمُ بأنّه في النهاية
that these images still have to work in the digital world.
لابدَّ من توفيرِ هذه الصّورِ بشكلٍ رقميّ.
There's no point in me putting all my blood, sweat and tears
أعني بأنّه لن يكونَ هناكَ معنىً لكلّ ما تعبت عليه
into these pictures
خلالَ إنتاجِ الصّور
if they're only going to be showing 500 pixels on a screen.
إنْ كانت ستكونُ مقيّدةً بدقّةِ الشاشةِ التي تراها من خلالها.
So with the help of Rob Chandler and Will Cookson,
لذا قمتُ معَ (روب تشاندلر) و (ويل كوكسون)
we developed a website
بتصميمِ موقعٍ على الانترنت
that enables the viewer to immerse themselves
يمكّنُ النّاسَ من الاستمتاعِ بمشاهدةِ الصورِ
into the full four-gigabyte files,
بدقّتها الأصليّة العالية
and they can explore all that microscopic detail.
وسيتمكّنون من رؤية أدقِّ تفاصيلِ المخلوق.
So if you have the time, and I encourage you,
وأنا أدعوكم حينما تجدونَ وقتاً
please visit microsculpture.net
لتصفّحِ الموقعِ microsculpture.net
and go and have a play.
تصفّحوه واستمتعوا
It's good fun.
إنّهُ مسلٍّ حقّاً.
I first showed the work at Oxford,
قمتُ بعرضِ الأعمالِ في أوكسفورد كبداية
and since then, it's moved on to the Middle East.
ومنذ ذلكَ الحينِ بدأتُ أعرضها في متاحفِ الشرقِ الأوسط.
It's now back in Europe and goes to Copenhagen this month.
ثمَّ أعدتها إلى أوروبا وهي في (كوبنهاغن) خلال هذا الشهر
And the feedback has been great.
وقد أحبّها الجميع.
You know, I get emails, actually, from all over the world --
وقد وردتني رسائلُ من أشخاصٍ من بلدانٍ عديدةٍ
from teachers, at the moment, who are using the website in school.
كمدرّسينَ مثلاً، يستخدمونَ هذه الصّورَ في المدرسةِ
The kids are using them on the tablet.
ليتفحّصها الأطفالُ على أجهزة التابلت.
They're zooming into the pictures
بالإمكانِ دوماً تكبيرُ الصّور واستخدامها
and using it for art class, biology class.
في دروسِ البيولوجيا مثلاً أو الفنون.
And that's not something I planned.
لم يكن هذا صراحةً شيئاً خططت لهُ
That's just a beautiful offshoot of the project.
بل كانَ شيئاً جميلاً نتجَ بسبب المشروع.
In fact, one of the things I like to do at the exhibitions
حقيقةً، أحبُّ جدّاً خلال فتراتِ المعارض
is actually look at the kiddies' reactions.
مشاهدةَ الأطفالِ عندَ رؤيتهم لهذهِ الصور.
And, you know, standing in front of a three-meter insect,
أعني، تخيّلوا طفلاً يقفُ بجوارِ حشرةٍ بطولِ ثلاثة أمتار
they could have been horrified.
على الأرجحِ سيكونُ خائفاً منها
But they're not. They look in wonder.
ولكنَّ على العكس! يقفُ الأطفالُ بذهولٍ
This little chap here, he stood there for five minutes, motionless.
كهذا الصبيِّ الذي بقيَ واقفاً يتأمّلُ دونَ حراكٍ لـ 5 دقائق.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And at the end of the day, actually, at the end of the day at the exhibitions,
وفي نهايةِ كلِّ يومٍ من أيّامِ المعرض
we have to wipe down the lower third of the big prints --
علينا دوماً أن ننظّفَ الثُلُثَ الأسفلَ من الصّور
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
just to remove all those sticky handprints,
لنُزيلَ البصماتِ التي يتركها الأطفال
because all they want to do is touch those big bugs.
لأنَّ كلَّ مايريدونَ فعلهُ هو لمسُ هذه الحشراتِ الكبيرة.
I do want to leave you with one final image, if that's OK.
أودُّ في النهاية لو سمحتم لي أن أترككم مع صورةٍ أخيرةٍ
This has to do with Charles Darwin.
تتعلّق بعضَ الشيءِ بـ (تشارلز داروِن).
One of the recent images that I photographed
واحدةٌ من الصّورِ التي التقطتها مؤخّراً
was this one here.
هي هذه الصورة.
I'm talking about the creature in the box, not my cat.
وبالتأكيدِ هي ليست صورةً لقطّتي بل للكائنِ الذي في العلبة.
And this is a shield bug
وهيَ حشرةٌ
that Charles Darwin brought back from Australia
جاءَ بها داروِن من أستراليا
on the HMS Beagle in 1836.
عندَ عودته من رحلتهِ الشهيرةِ عامَ 1836.
And when I got it home,
أمّا أنا فعِندَ عودتي للمنزل
I stood in my kitchen and stared at it for about 20 minutes.
فقد وقفتُ أحدِّق في هذه الحشرةِ لحواليّ 20 دقيقةً في المطبخ
I couldn't believe I was in possession of this beautiful creature.
لم أصدّق حينها بأنّني حظيتُ بفرصةِ امتلاكِ هذا المخلوقِ الجميل.
And at that moment, I kind of realized
في تلكَ اللحظةِ تماماً، أحسستُ بأنّني
that this validated the project for me.
رضيتُ عن هذا المشروع.
The fact that the museum was willing to risk me playing with this
حقيقةُ أنّ إدارةَ المتحفِ خاطرتْ بإعطائي كائناً بهذه الأهميّة
kind of showed me that my images had worth --
أشعرني بأنَّ أعمالي هي فعلاً ذاتُ أهميّة
you know, they weren't disposable.
وبأنَّ عدستي لم تفقد قيمتها بعد.
That's the image that I produced.
وهذهِ هيَ الصّورةُ التي التقطتها حينها.
I often wonder, still, when I look at this:
أحياناً لا زلتُ أفكّر حينَ أرى هذه الصّورة
What would Charles Darwin make of these images?
"ماذا كانَ داروِن سيفعلُ لو امتلكَ هذه الصّورة؟"
Do you think he'd like his picture of his shield bug? I hope so.
هل تعتقدونَ بأنّهُ كانَ سيحبُّها؟ أتمنّى هذا.
So --
إذاً ...
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
You know, I think it's strange in a way.
حقيقةً، الأمرُ غريبٌ قليلاً
I'm a visual person, I'm a creative person,
يفترضُ بي بحكمِ مهنتي بأنّني شخصٌ مُبدع
but I still needed the eyes of a child to find my extraordinary subject.
لكنّني لم أكنْ لأتمكّنَ من أنْ أُطلقَ العنانَ لمخيّلتي لولا عينيّ سيباستيان.
That's the way it was.
هذا ما حدثَ فعلاً.
So all I can say is, thank you very much, Sebastian;
لذا فكلُّ ما بإمكاني قوله هو: شكراً جزيلاً سيباستيان
I am very, very grateful.
إنّني حقّاً ممتنٌّ لك.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)